Miscellaneous letters collection
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
- Jenner, Edward, Berkeley, [England], to "Dear Madam" [Lady Ducie], 1822 July 28 (Box 2 G-L)
  According to a letter from William LeFanu to John F. Fulton, 13 January 1956, the recipient was the wife of the first Earl Ducie. Her eldest daughter, Lady Mary Moreton married the 7th Earl of Denbigh in May 1822. The letter discusses the case of Lady Denbigh who was vaccinated but contracted smallpox. Jenner notes the improvements made in his methods of vaccination since vaccinating Lady Denbigh. Purchased by John F. Fulton from M. Sinelnikoff, New York, July 1954. Typed transcript available.
- Jenner, Edward, Berkeley, [England], to Gardner, 1806 June 26 (Box 2 G-L)
  Letter from Edward Jenner to Gardner, otherwise unidentified, inviting him to attend on the day appointed for "spider smothering."
- Jenner, Edward, to Charles Parry, Crescent, Bath, no date (Box 2 G-L)
  Letter from Edward Jenner to Charles Henry Parry reflecting on disease, sorrow, and death in his own family and in that of Parry, and in particular on the suffering of Parry's father, Caleb Hillier Parry.
  Purchased from Zeitlin & Verbrugge, Los Angeles, 1959. Typed transcript available.
- Jennings, Hargrave, [London], to "Dear Madam", 1883 August 2 (Box 2 G-L)
  Gift of L. Cohen, Argosy, 1952.
- Johnston, John, Wesleyan University, Middletown, to Messrs. Hezekiah Howe & Co., 1837 February 21 (Box 2 G-L)
  Johnston was Profesor of Natural Sciences at Wesleyan. The letter concerns his subscription to Benjamin Silliman's American Journal of Science.
- Jones, Henry Bence, London, to Dr. Becker, 1852 August 10 (Box 2 G-L)
- Jowett, Benjamin, Oxford, to [E. Ray Lankester], 18-- November 19 (Box 2 G-L)
  On the medical profession in Oxford. Letter purchased from I.K. Fletcher, September 1942.
- Keen, William Williams, Philadelphia, to Walter R. Steiner, Hartford, 1922 June 15 (Box 2 G-L)
  Thanks Steiner for his help on the contributions of New England surgeons. He has decided on a different topic for his presentation.
- Keith, Arthur, Sir, Royal College of Surgeons, London, to Mrs. Thorne, 1929 March 22 (Box 2 G-L)
  Keith wrote to Mrs. Thorne, "Your father deserves all you can do for his memory." The letter was given to Fulton by Dr. Backer. Folder contains also a letter from John F. Fulton to Sir Arthur Keith, 1954 January 7, asking who Mrs. Thorne was; Keith's reply, 1954 January 12, saying that he did not recall; and Fulton's response, 1954 January 16. The 1954 letters also discuss the death of the anthropologist Ralph Linton and the Piltdown man affair.
- Kershaw, Richard, Central London Throat and Ear Hospital, 2 letters to to Dr. Macintyre, 1909 March 6 - 1909 March 9 (Box 2 G-L)
  On how Dr. Kershaw handles asking patients for contributions toward their care. The letter was removed from the Historical Library's copy of Richard Kershaw, Special Hospitals (London, 1909).
- Kingsbury, John A., Milbank Memorial Fund, to C.-E. A. Winslow, New Haven, and reply, 1929 March 11 - 1929 March 20 (Box 2 G-L)
  On public health reports made by Sir Arthur Newsholme in the counties of Gloucester and Cambridge, England.
- Kneeland, Samuel, Mass. Institute of Technology, Boston, to I. I. Hayes, 1874 June 11 (Box 2 G-L)
  Kneeland, a physician and naturalist, asks the Arctic explorer, I. I. Hayes, M.D., to join him on a trip to Iceland. Letter was purchased from W. R. Benjamin, September 1941.
- Knight, Jonathan, New Haven, to Dr. David B. W. Shaw, Woodbury, 1860 April 8 (Box 2 G-L)
  Knight plans to travel to Woodbury on Tuesday and perform the operation on Wednesday. He makes suggestions to Dr. Shaw on how to treat the patient before the operation. Letter from H.W. Liebert, March 30, 1965.
- Knighton, William, Sir, Windsor Castle, to Charles Bell, [1826] October 16 (Box 2 G-L)
  Thanks Bell for two papers on the nerves and says that he has no chance of becoming acquainted with the physician Bell mentions. Purchased from Myers & Co., January 1950. Also a postcard by Myers & Co. offering another Knighton letter.
- Kronecker, Hugo, to Charlotte Kronecker, 1913 August 12 (Box 2 G-L)
  Gift of Mme. Charlotte Kronecker to John F. Fulton, November 1946.
- Kronecker, Hugo, Universitat Bern, to the editor of the Index Catalog of the Surgeon-General's Ofice, Washington, D.C., 1897 April 11 (Box 2 G-L)
  From W. W. Francis, February 24, 1948.
- La Condamine, Charles-Marie de, Paris, to [J. A. de Luc], 1761 August 15 (Box 2 G-L)
- Laennec, R. T. H., to Monsieur Pillet, no year October[?] 10 (Box 2 G-L)
  With an additional half sheet that may or may not be related. Removed from Laennec, Propositions sur la doctrine d'Hippocrate (Paris, 1804),
- Larrey, D. J., Koenigsburg, to [?], Chirurgien Mayer, 1812 October 27 (Box 2 G-L)
  Removed from L.-J.-B. Béringer-Féraud, Le Baron Hippolyte Larrey (Paris, 1899). Letter may be missing the bottom portion.
- Lewes, George Henry, 9 letters, 1847? - 1866? (Box 2 G-L)
  Two letters dated Dresden, 1858 July 23 and 1859 March 1, are to John Chapman. The first describes his travels and visits with anatomists and physiologists. Two letters may be to T. H. Lacy and the remainder are to unidentified recipients. Five letters have been transcribed by Gordon Haight.
  Purchased by John F. Fulton from Myers & Co., London. Folder includes correspondence among Meyers & Co., Gordon Haight, and Jonn Fulton, 1951-1953, and a sheet of writing which has a newspaper notice of the George Henry Lewes Studentship founded in memory of Lewes to support research in physiology.
- Lindsey, Theophilus, London, to William Tayleur, Shrewsbury, 1786 May 17 (Box 2 G-L)
  On Joseph Priestley, religion, and a plan for a new seminary.
- Lister, Joseph, Baron, 2 letters to Mrs. Bishop, 1886 February 21 - 1886 March 7 (Box 2 G-L)
  On the illness and death of her husband Dr. Bishop. Purchased by John F. Fulton from H.K. Elliott, London, August 1956.
- Lister, Joseph, Baron [London], to Sir William Osler, 1907 January 13 (Box 2 G-L)
  On making a list of American surgeons of special distinction and Osler's mother's 100th birthday. Removed from Sir Rickman John Godlee, Lord Lister (Oxford, 1924).
- Lister, Joseph, Baron, to W. B. Holderness [incomplete], ca. 1867-1868 (Box 2 G-L)
  Two pages on preventing putrefaction of wounds. The first part of the letter is missing. The folder contains additional materials on the provenance of the letter which was removed from Holderness's copy of volume 3 of St. George's Hospital Reports. These include a letter from Sir W. Hale White to W. B. Holderness, 1914 January 28; a copy of a letter from Harvey Cushing to Archibald Malloch, New York Academy of Medicine, 1930 March 4; a letter from Eric Bligh (bookseller) to John F. Fulton, 1930 March 9. Also related is a photostat of a letter in the Osler Library from Lister to Malloch, 1868 September 10.
- Loewi, Otto, New York, to William T. Salter, New Haven, 1951 June 13 (Box 2 G-L)
  Thanks Salter for his hospitality in New Haven where he received an honorary degree from Yale University in 1951. He includes two brief accounts of the dream that led to his experiment on the frog's heart, showing the chemical transmission of the nervous impulse. Also included is a copy of the Commencement Program inscribed by Loewi to the Department of Pharmacology at Yale. Gift of William T. Salter, June 18, 1951.
- Lovell, Joseph, Washington, D.C., to Col. Thomas Aspinwall, U.S. Consul at London, 1829 September 16 (Box 2 G-L)
  From the bequest of Harvey Cushing.
- Lowe, John, Gull, William, and Jenner, William, bulletin on the state of health of the Prince of Wales, 1871 December 15 (Box 2 G-L)
  "His Royal Highness the Prince of Wales has passed a tranquil morning. The Symptoms are still favorable." Signed by William Jenner, M.D., William Gull, M.D., and John Lowe, M.D. Letter donated by Bern Dibner, March 1969.
- Luc, J. A. de (Jean André), London, to Alessandro Volta, Pavia, and reply by Volta, no date - 1783 August 20 (Box 2 G-L)
  Fourteen-page letter by de Luc on electricity and Volta's six-page reply. Letters purchased by john Fulton from Bader, Geneva, ca. 1948.
- Lyell, Charles, to Gideon Mantell, 1835 (postmark) (Box 2 G-L)
  Birthday gift to John F. Fulton from A. Muirhead, 1947.
- Lyell, Charles [London], to [?], 1850 October 22 (Box 2 G-L)
  Removed from Leonard Huxley, Life and Letters of Thomas Henry Huxley(London, 1903).
- Macaulay, James, London, to Mr. Hall, 1880 March 9 (Box 3 M-Sh)
  On letterhead of The Leisure Hour, for which Mrs. Hall wrote a piece. Gift of L. Cohen, Argosy, 1952.
- Macaulay, T. B., Albany, to "My dear Sir", 1855 November 13 (Box 3 M-Sh)
  From the collection of Dr. Henry Kirke Cushing.
- Mailhouse, Max, New Haven, to Henry L. Swain, New Haven, 1937 July 3 (Box 3 M-Sh)
  Sends two poems, one on forming the New Haven Medical Association Library, 1899, and one on Charles Tuttle. Donated to the Library by Herbert Thoms, October 16, 1947.
- Malpighi, Marcello, Bologna, to "Illustrissimo et Eccelentissimo Signor", 1676 April 25 (Box 3 M-Sh)
  With typed transcript and translation. Purchased by John Fulton, September 1956, in Florence, Italy, via J. Zeitlin.
- Malthus, Thomas R., to J. L. Mallet, London, 1834 November 13 (Box 3 M-Sh)
  Letter concerns population, poverty, statistics, and the work of Sir Francis d'Ivernois. Purchased from Goodspeed's Book Shop, Boston, ca. 1965.
- Marcet, Alexandre-John-Gaspard, 8 letters and documents to and by Marcet, 1808-1820 (Box 3 M-Sh)
  Marcet was a physician and chemist who lectured at Guy's Hospital, London. Documents include: Printed resolution addressed to Marcet and hand-signed by William Livingston, naming him an honorary member of the Aberdeen Medical Society, 1808 October 20; C. Duméril, Secrétaire de la Société de Médecine de la Faculté de Paris, to Marcet, naming him a corresponding member, 1816 August 27; Acloque [a firm], Paris, to Marcet, 1820 July 14 and 1820 August 31; Henry Lemercier, pharmacien-manufacturier de produits chemiques, to Marcet, 1820 July 14; Pixii [firm], Paris, to Marcet, 1820 August 1; printed pamphlet to Fellows of the Royal Society, on the politics of electing a new Chair and discouraging private attempts to select Humphry Davy, 1820 November; handwritten copy of Marcet to C. Duméril, membre de l'Institut, Paris, [no year] September 14.
  Purchased from Libraire Ancienne P.-L. Bader, May 1958. See also letters to Marcet under Louis Odier and Jean-Louis Prévost.
- Marie, Pierre, to Esther Rosencrantz, San Francisco, 1928 December 26 (Box 3 M-Sh)
  With envelope; and carbon copy of letter from Esther Rosencrantz to Pierre Marie, 1928 November 18.The letters concern Dr. Rosencrantz leaving a copy of a memorial volume to Sir William Osler (to which she had contributed) at Pierre Marie's home in Paris for him to sign.
  The folder also contains Esther Rosencranz's reminiscences of Pierre Marie, undated; Esther Rosencrantz to John Fulton, 1948 November 16; and a copy of letter from John Fulton to Esther Rosencrantz, 1948 November 7. Dr. Rosencrantz donated Pierre Marie's letter to John Fulton and the Historical Library.
- Martin, H. N., Woodville, to Dr. Benjamin D. Neill, near Tchula, Holmes County, Mississippi, 1836 June 12 (Box 3 M-Sh)
  Newsy letter by Martin, a physician and seller of drugs. Letter sent to John Fulton by Mr. Ralph Hubell, October 8, 1938.
- McCormick, Harold, Chicago, to George M. Smith, Pine Orchard, Conn., 1937 September 27 (Box 3 M-Sh)
- Mease, James, Philadelphia, to Messrs. C.W. Karthaus, Kurts & Co., Baltimore, 1829 February 12 (Box 3 M-Sh)
  On behalf of the Horticultural Society of Philadelphia, Mease would like to forward a packet containing a letter to the horticultural society at Brussels and a copy of the Philadelphia society's Constitution to a similar society being formed in Amsterdam. He hopes for a friendly exchange of trees, plants, and seeds. The letter was the gift of J. Cohen, Argosy, 1952.
- Mesmer, Franz Anton, to Monsieur le Marquis de Chefdebièn, Narbonne or Carcassonne, ca. 1785-1786 (Box 3 M-Sh)
- Miltenberger, George W., Dean of the Faculty of Physic, University of Maryland, to Sheridan Muspratt, 1858 March 15 (Box 3 M-Sh)
  The letter notes the action of the Faculty of Physic in conferring an honorary M.D. to Sheridan Muspratt, Ph.D., F.R.S.E [Fellow of the Royal Society of Edinburgh]. Folder also includes a printed broadside, Translation of Dr. Muspratt's American Diploma, University of Maryland (Liverpool: Henry Greenwood, Steam Printing Works, ca. 1858).
- Minkowski, M., Hirnanatomisches Institut der Universitat Zurich, to Milton C. Winternitz, Yale University School of Medicine, 1926 January 22 (Box 3 M-Sh)
  Includes carbon copy of Winternitz to Minkowski, 1926 January 12, introducing Dr. James C. Fox, Assistant Professor of Medicine, who is hoping to work at Minkowski's Institute. Minkowski replies that he is pleased that Dr. Fox has chosen "our Institute."
- Mitchell, S. Weir, Philadelphia, to Dr. Massey, no date (Box 3 M-Sh)
  About setting up an appointment. His fee for a half day's absence is $100.
- Mivart, St. Geoge Jackson, Hurstcote, Chilworth, Surrey, to "Dear Sir", 1890 January 7 (Box 3 M-Sh)
  Purchased from D.A. Berry, January 1963.
- Moffatt, Thomas, New London, Conn., to Dudley Woodbridge, Norwich, Conn., 1771 May 10 (Box 3 M-Sh)
  Provides a regimen for Mr. Woodbridge to follow until their next meeting. Purchased by John Fulton from Frances Edwards, Old Books, Hartford, February 1941. With Frances Edwards to Fulton, 1941 February 11, and a page on Thomas Moffatt, a Scotch physician who emigrated to America in 1746.
- Monsey, Messenger, Norwich, to Lady Walpole, 1768 August 17 (Box 3 M-Sh)
  Gift of Herman W. Liebert, Beinecke Library, to Frederick Kilgour, Director, Yale Medical Library, 1963. Includes a carbon of a letter from Kilgour to Liebert, 1963 October 24.
- Moore, Norman, London, to Dr. Cock, 1912 November 6 (Box 3 M-Sh)
  Madeline Stanton annotated the letter, "Found in basket on Dr. Cushing's desk at home." Also included is a later typed copy of a letter from Sir Norman Moore to William Osler, 1910 April 4, with Harvey Cushing's annotation, "Norman Moore to WO."
- Morgan, Charles F., Greenville, Michigan, certification that Samuel E. Morgan pursued the study of medicine and surgery under him for three years, 1874 December 18 (Box 3 M-Sh)
  Samuel Ernest Morgan graduated from the Medical Institution of Yale College in 1875. This certification was probably sent to the medical school in fulfillment of the requirements for graduation. This is a late example of a medical apprenticeship, as this was no longer required at Yale after 1879.
- Morrison, Albert, to Clarissa E. Morrison, and letters and receipts to Albert Morrison, ca. 1845-1872 (Box 3 M-Sh)
  Albert Morrison (1820-1873), born in Hebron, Connecticut, was attending the Pittsfield Medical College, when he wrote to his sister Clarissa, asking for monetary help and discussing visiting her. He graduated from the College of Physicians and Surgeons, New York City, in 1847, and practiced in Windsor, Connecticut. The folder also contains four letters to Morrison and a receipt, (1) from his mentor Dr. M. L. Libbie of Broad Brook, Conn., 1847 February 1, sending Morrrison his certificate of apprenticeship [not in the folder] and discussing Morrison's forthcoming medical school examination; (2) from C. F. Vincent, Tariffville, Conn., 1851 April 5; and (3-4) two invitations to annual meetings of the Hartford County Medical Society, from H.S. Fuller, clerk, 1871 April 10 and 1872 April 20. The receipt is for dues from the Connecticut Medical Society, 1866 April 10.
- Mott, Valentine, New York, to Dr. De Rosset [?], 1825 July 18 (Box 3 M-Sh)
  Mott responds to a case presented to him by another doctor. De Rosset may be Dr. Armand John De Rosset (1767-1859). Also included in the file is a signed slip, "Address to the Academy of Medicine on retiring from the Presidency." From the bequest of Harvey Cushing.
- Müller, Friedrich Max, Oxford, to E. Ray Lankester, 1878 November 3 (Box 3 M-Sh)
  Concerning having a Medical Faculty at Oxford in addition to a finishing school for gentlemen. Purchased from I.K. Fletcher, September 1942.
- Naegeli, [Otto?] Kantonsspital Zürich, to Arnold C. Klebs, Nyon, 1933 May 4 (Box 3 M-Sh)
- Neander, Gustaf, Stockholm, to Arnold C. Klebs, Nyon, 1928 November 19 (Box 3 M-Sh)
- Needham, Joseph, University of Cambridge, to C. N. H. Long, Yale University School of Medicine, 1940 March 27 (Box 3 M-Sh)
  Letter supports the application of Dr. Gwei-Djen Lu, for a research fellowship in biochemistry at Yale. He praises Dr. Lu, a Chinese woman biochemist, who received her Ph.D. from Cambridge, as "one of the best Chinese minds" in biochemistry. She later became Needham's chief co-author and much later his wife.
- Nightingale, Frances, South W. Park Lane, to "My dear Sir", 18-- March 26 (Box 3 M-Sh)
  From the mother of Florence Nightingale to an unidentified recipient on the portrait of her daughter and her daughter's state of health. Gift of H.W. Liebert, November 1961.
- Noyes, Burr, New Haven, 3 letters to Charles L. Mills, Fairfield, 1824-1825 (Box 3 M-Sh)
  Burr Noyes and Charles Lewis Mills both graduated from Yale College in 1924. The letters were written while Noyes was a medical student at the Medical Institution of Yale College. He mentions Jonathan Knight's anatomy class. Noyes received his M.D. in 1827. The letters were donated by Miss Catherine Curtis, Charlottesville, Va., a great niece of Mills, in 1967.
- Odier, Louis, Geneva, 8 letters to Alexandre-John-Gaspard Marcet, 1794 August 30 - 1815 December 4? (Box 3 M-Sh)
  Dr. Louis Odier of Geneva brought cowpox from England to the Continent and used the term "vaccine." Letters, which mention inoculation for smallpox, were purchased from Bader, May 1958.
- O'Donoghue, Edward Geoffrey, Bethlem Royal Hospital, London, to Dr. Percy Smith, 1914, October 19 (Box 3 M-Sh)
  Labeled "Private." On the hospital. Letter removed from O'Donoghue's The Story of Bethlehem Hospital(1914).
- Oliver, William, Bath, to Mr. Marriott, Fellow of Pembroke College in Cambridge, 1727 November 7 (Box 3 M-Sh)
  William Oliver (1695-1764) was a physician and inventor of the "Bath Oliver." Letter purchased from Myers & Co., 1943.
- Olmsted, Denison, Yale College, to Elijah Ward, Clinton House, New York, 1839 May 20 (Box 3 M-Sh)
  Olmsted, professor of natural history and astronomy at Yale College, agrees to a series of 10 lectures on astronomy if he can obtain leave from Yale. Letter acquired from Henry Schuman, January 1947.
- Osler, William, Sir, 9 letters to Walter R. Steiner, 1906 June 29 - 1919 April 17 (Box 3 M-Sh)
  Letters dated 1906 June 19, 1908 September 22, 1909 December 30, 1911 October 3, 1912 October 7, [1912] November 7, 1916 March 31, 1917 January 22, 1919 April 17. From Miss Amy L. Steiner, April 1943.
- Osler, William, Sir, Oxford, to "Owen", no date (Box 3 M-Sh)
  Osler declines a dinner invitation because he lectures at 5 pm. Letter is the gift of Joan K. Jackson, Bethany, Conn., November 2001.
- [Osler, William, Sir] 6 letters to Sir William Osler on medicine at Oxford, 1907 February 1907- 1908 March 18 (Box 3 M-Sh)
  The letters discuss fields for medical examinations at Oxford and the place of pharmacology at Oxford. Authors include W. Ramsden, W. E. Dixon, Arthur Cushny, E. S. Craig, and an unidentified author. Presumably these letters were sent to Harvey Cushing who was writing Osler's biography.
- Owen, Richard, College of Surgeons, London, to Dr. F. [Francis?] Boott., 1836 December 20 (Box 3 M-Sh)
  Concerning the possible exchange of specimens between the College of Surgeons and the "Boston Museum" under Dr. John Collins Warren.
- Paget, James, Sir, Saint Bartholomew's Hospital [London], to J. Domesed [?] Esq., 1852 October 16 (Box 3 M-Sh)
  An acknowledgement of student fees. Donated by Dr. Geoffrey M. Coley, Hartford, October 1962.
- Paine, Samuel, Capt., Lebanon, N.H., to Col. Jonathan Chase, Cornish, N.H., 1777 March 14 (Box 3 M-Sh)
  On a "Class a going into the pest house tomorrow" to take inoculation for smallpox during the Revolutionary War. He hopes Chase will come. Letter from H. W. Liebert, April 1958.
- Papaspyros, N. S., London, to Geoffrey Keynes, 1952 July 22 (Box 3 M-Sh)
- Parkman, G., Boston, to "G. Hayward, M.D. & c", 1846 February 23 (Box 3 M-Sh)
  The writer may be George Parkman. He suggests larger dimensions for an unidentified building project. Madeline Stanton suggested that the letter may have been given br Dr. J. Collins Warren to Harvey Cushing.
- Pasteur, Louis, Paris to Monsieur, 1863 August 7 (Box 3 M-Sh)
  Purchased from Goodspeed's Book Shop, Boston. Translation available.
- Peaslee, Edmund Randolph, 11 letters to Amassa Farrington Kinne, 1838 January 16 - 1840 February 12 (Box 3 M-Sh)
  Edmund Randolph Peaslee graduated from Dartmouth College in 1836 and from the Medical Institution of Yale College in 1840. This series of letters were written during the end of his studies at Dartmouth through his time as a medical student at Yale. Kinne graduated from Dartmouth College in 1837 and was a roommate of Peaslee. He obtained his M.D. from Dartmouth in 1840. The letters were donated by Genevieve K. Bartlett, widow of Dr. Charles J. Bartlett, of New Haven. Extracts were published by Herbert Thoms, "Some Letters of of Edmund Randolph Peaslee B.A. Dartmouth 1836, M.D. Yale 1840," Yale Journal of Biology and Medicine, 17[6] (July 1945): 685-704. The folder includes the original letters, transcripts, and correspondence of Mrs. Bartlett and Herbert Thoms concerning biographical material on Kinne.
- Pershing, John J., 9 letters to Rev. Charles S. McFarland, Federal Council of Churches, New York, and others concerning chaplains in the Army and Navy, 1919-1928 (Box 3 M-Sh)
  Seven letters of General Pershing are to Rev. Charles S. McFarland, Secretary of the American Federation of Churches, New York. The letters were purchased by George Milton Smith and donated to the Historical Library in June and July 1950. Included in the folder is correspondence between Smith and John Fulton concerning the gift.
- Pickering, Timothy, Salem, to John Skinner, Post Master, Baltimore, 1823 March 14 (Box 3 M-Sh)
  Concerns a parcel of Egyptian millet seed and his subscription to the American Farmer. Letter purchased from F.H. Sweet and donated by John Fulton, ca. 1959.
- Prescott, Benjamin T., Meredith Village, N.H., to Levi Bartlett, Kingston, N.H., 1826 January 24 (Box 3 M-Sh)
  Levi Bartlett appears to have been a mentor who had loaned Prescott medical books. Prescott describes his informal apprenticeship to Dr. Simeon Dana, with whom he boarded "in and about New Hampton, N.H.," for 16 weeks; his early medical practice in Meredith; and which other doctors are practicing nearby. The letter was purchased from Symmachus Trading Co., Boston, in 1950.
- Prévost, Jean-Louis, Geneva, to [Alexandre-John-Gaspard] Marcet, 1821 December 7 (Box 3 M-Sh)
  On vaccination. Letter purchased May 1958.
- Ramsay, David, "Head of Bohemia" [Maryland] to Thomas Bradford, Philadelphia, 1772 June 3 (Box 3 M-Sh)
  Orders medical books from Thomas Bradford. The letter was purchased by George Milton Smith and given to Harvey Cushing in April 1938.
- Remak, Robert, Berlin, to "Professor Dr. Krause," Hannover, 1838 June 1 (Box 3 M-Sh)
  Removed from Library's copy of Robert Remak, Observationes anatomicae et microscopicae de systematis nervosi structura(1838).
- Retzius, Gustaf, Stockholm, to "Hochgeehrter Herr Doktor", 1896 May 3 (Box 3 M-Sh)
  Removed from Library's copy of Gustaf Retzius, Biologische Untersuchungen (1881).
- Richardson M[aurice] H., Boston, to O.T. Osborne, 1899 March 20 (Box 3 M-Sh)